Guide to the David G. Henderson papers, 1926-1988 MS2173
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
David G. Henderson papers
1926-1988
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Henderson, David G.
MS2173
4.75 Linear Feet
Collection contains memoranda, correspondence, reports, handbooks, publications, articles, bibliographies, conference materials, photographs, catalogs, notes, and architectural drawings collected by David G. Henderson in the course of his career as an architect for the National Park Service. The material dates from 1926-88 (bulk: 1963-82). The collection deals with issues of historic preservation. It includes internal National Park Service memoranda, guidelines, procedures, and policies, as well as general background information about the preservation and restoration of historic structures. The collection also includes plans and reports for the restoration and maintenance of several national parks and historic sites around the United States.
Box S0001
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by David G. Henderson in 1990. A number of books were included with this donation. They have been separated from the manuscript materials and are now housed in the general collection.
Historical or Biographical Note
David G. Henderson worked as an architect specializing in historic preservation. He was employed by the National Park Service's Office of Environmental Planning and Design's Denver Service Center and Eastern Service Center.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains memoranda, correspondence, reports, handbooks, publications, articles, bibliographies, conference materials, photographs, catalogs, notes, and architectural drawings collected by David G. Henderson in the course of his career as an architect for the National Park Service. The material dates from 1926-88 (bulk: 1963-82). The collection deals with issues of historic preservation. It includes internal National Park Service memoranda, guidelines, procedures, and policies, as well as general background information about the preservation and restoration of historic structures. The collection also includes plans and reports for the restoration and maintenance of several national parks and historic sites around the United States.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: Subject files and Reports and plans.
Preservation and restoration; Historic buildings; Photographs; Conservation and restoration; Historic preservation; United States. National Park Service
- Subject files, 1926-1988; MS 2173 Series 1; 3.5 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 10)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains memoranda, correspondence, reports, handbooks, publications, articles, bibliographies, conference materials, photographs, catalogs, notes, and architectural drawings collected by David G. Henderson in the course of his career as an architect for the National Park Service. The material dates from 1926-88 (bulk: 1963-83). The series includes internal National Park Service memoranda, guidelines, procedures, and policies, as well as general background information about the preservation and restoration of historic structures. Of particular interest are materials relating to the restoration of the White House.
  - Access for handicapped, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Amateur's Guide to Terms Commonly Used in Describing Historic Buildings, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Architectural history, style charts, etc., 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Association for Preservation Technology, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Attingham, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin--Cultural resources management, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Classified structure field inventory report--Inter 5323-75, 05/05/1975-02/13/1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Concrete, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conference on conservation of historic stone buildings and monuments, 02/02/1981-02/04/1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The conservation of stone, 03/1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Development corporation, 06/16/1971-01/06/1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Epoxy, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Export summaries, 07/05/1988-08/19/1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Federal architecture: Adaptive-use facilities--Staff report, 05/1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Historic preservation and stablization class "C" estimating manual, 07/1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Historic Denver, inc., 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Historic and prehistoric structures handbook, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Historic American buildings survey, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Masonry cleaning--10G clearance, 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Masonry cleaning, 05/02/1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Text on photograph: "Dry Sandblasting North Face, West End, South Wing, May 2, 1979"
  - Masonry cleaning, 05/02/1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Text on photograph: "Wet Aggregate, North Face, West End, South Wing, May 2, 1979"
  - Masonry cleaning, 05/02/1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Text on photograph: "Water Jet North Face, West End, South Wing - May 2, 1979 - started at 1,000 p.s.i.--increased to 2,000 p.s.i"
  - Masonry cleaning, 05/02/1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Text on photograph: "Paint Stripper North Face, West End, South Wing May 2, 1979"
  - Masonry cleaning (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Masonry cleaning (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Masonry cleaning (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Masonry cleaning (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Masonry, mortar, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Masonry workshop--APT--Campbell Center / Weaver-Weiss Mt. Carroll, Ill., 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Metal corrosion, 1967-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Moisture intrusion--Built-up roofs, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nails and hardware, 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Conservation Advisory Council, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Park Service cultural resources managament guidelines December 1981[1/2], 12/1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Park Service cultural resources management guidelines December 1981 [2/2], 12/1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Park Service design standards, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Park Service management policies [1/3], 1963-1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Park Service management policies [2/3], 1963-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Park Service management policies [3/3], 1963-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Park Service standards guidelines for cultural resources, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National Park Service technical preservation services division [1/2], 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Park Service technical preservation services division [2/2], 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - National register historic landmarks--Historic survey, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National trust for historic preservation, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Office of environmental planning and design memoranda, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Old House journal, 1975 ca. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Paint, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Philosophy / approach, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Planning conference--Albright Mar-71 [1/2], 1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Planning conference--Albright Mar-71-Images [2/2], 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Text on photograph: "United States Department of the Interior, National Park Service, Horace M. Albright Training Academy, Orientation to Park Planning, March 22-26, 1971" Caption includes names of people in photograph.
  - Planning--General policies and procedures, 07/1967-05/1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Preservation--Investigation techniques and methods, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Publications and reading lists--O.A.H.P., N.B.S., etc., 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Rectified photography and photo drawings for historic preservation, 12/1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Restoration guidelines, 1940 ca.-1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Solmica, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Stone [1/2], 1972-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Stone [2/2] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Technical preservation services division--O.A.H.P. / H.C.R.S., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Third annual historic structures training conference, 08/09/1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Transportation: National parks (review draft), 07/1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - White House [1/2], 1926-1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    A set of architectural drawings have been removed from this folder and placed in MS2173-S001#00001.
  - White House [2/2], 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Wood, 1952-1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Design and planning drawings, 1970-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Thaddeus Kosciuszko National Memorial drawings, 07/1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Reports and Plans, 1968-1982; MS 2173 Series 2; 1.25 Linear feet (Box 8, Box 6, Box 7)
  This series contains master plans, historic structure reports, studies and other documents related to several national parks and historic sites around the United States. The material dates from 1968-82. David Henderson either wrote or contributed to most of these documents. In addition to providing detailed architectural information about the historic sites, the documents also describe the history of the sites and their role in the larger community and region. They provide a framework for the cultural and historical interpretation of the sites and structures they describe.
  - Fort McHenry--Master plan, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hampton--Purpose and objectives (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Home of Franklin D. Roosevelt--Master plan preliminary draft (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Home of Franklin D. Roosevelt--Final Environment Statement, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Hot Springs--Master plan, 05/1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Independence--Master plan, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Jefferson--Old Courthouse--Energy conservation survey, 07/1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Jefferson--Old Courthouse--Historic struction report--Historic data section (part 1) and historic grounds survey, 01/1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial--Specifications, 07/1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minute Man--Historic structure report, 03/1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Nez Perce--St. Joseph's Mission Church--Historic structure report, 02/1974 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Nez Perce--Historic structure report, 01/1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Nez Perce--Historic structure report--St. Joseph's Mission historical data, 05/1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Salem Maritime--Interpretive prospectus, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - St. Gaudens--Master plan, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - St. Croix Island--Assessment of alternatives, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Thaddeus Kosciuszko National Memorial--Specifications (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Vanderbilt Mansion--Final master plan, 01/1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Whiskeytown--Historic structure report, 05/1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Wolf Trap Farm Park--Master plan, 10/1970 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Yellowstone--Old Faithful Inn--Historic structure report, historic data section, 01/1982 (Box 8, Folder 8)